<schedule>
  <version>2019-12-14 02:00; open-infra 4; chaoszone 0.1</version>
  <conference>
    <acronym>36C3</acronym>
    <title>36. Chaos Communication Congress</title>
    <start>2019-12-26</start>
    <end>2019-12-30</end>
    <days>5</days>
    <timeslot_duration>00:15</timeslot_duration>
  </conference>
  <day index="1" date="2019-12-26" start="2019-12-26T06:00:00+01:00" end="2019-12-27T04:00:00+01:00">
    <room name="Lecture room 11"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 14-15"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 13"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M1"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M2"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M3"/>
    <room name="Kidspace"/>
    <room name="CCL Saal 3"/>
    <room name="Chaos West Bühne"/>
    <room name="ChaosZone"/>
    <room name="OIO Stage"/>
  </day>
  <day index="2" date="2019-12-27" start="2019-12-27T06:00:00+01:00" end="2019-12-28T04:00:00+01:00">
    <room name="Lecture room 11"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 14-15"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 13"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M1"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M2"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M3"/>
    <room name="Kidspace"/>
    <room name="CCL Saal 3"/>
    <room name="Chaos West Bühne"/>
    <room name="ChaosZone"/>
    <room name="OIO Stage">
      <event id="376" guid="989bacb7-b112-5f02-afc3-6c112aab3435">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T10:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>10:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>RSGMFF</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/RSGMFF/</url>
        <title>Generalprobe Stage</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Finales Trockenschwimmen auf der Bühne mit Licht, Ton, Video, Streaming</abstract>
        <description>Speaker wird noch gesucht für Powerpoint-Karaoke oder "Autocomplete Texting" (requires audience)</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="6">
            <code>HFER8G</code>
            <public_name>Adorfer</public_name>
            <biography>In "[Tier][1][netzen][2]" aufgewachsen, vom "[Knastfunk][3]" sozialisiert, &#13;
hat mal mit [waffle][4] und [KA9Q][5] angefangen und den Einstieg zu TCP/IP über [AX.25][6] gefunden.&#13;
Erste Begegnung mit Mesh-Funknetzen: "PublicDomain87" (FoeBUDe.V./Bunker Ulmenwall/Bielefeld/1998): "[DIRC -- kostenloses Telefonnetz" mit Winrich Hoseit, Köln][7])&#13;
&#13;
  [1]: http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/FidoNet&#13;
  [2]: http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Janus_%28Protokoll%29&#13;
  [3]: http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/CB-Funk&#13;
  [4]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waffle_%28BBS_software%29&#13;
  [5]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KA9Q&#13;
  [6]: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AX.25&#13;
  [7]: http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-8778738.html</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="379" guid="a01886bc-c6f6-5598-bdef-59d89b73def5">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T13:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>13:00</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>DQ3DBL</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/DQ3DBL/</url>
        <title>Opening Session</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Eröffnung des OIO, der Bühne und Vorstellung aller Assemblies auf dem OIO</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="139">
            <code>GDG8D9</code>
            <public_name>Peter</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="365" guid="1cc57eb1-b131-5ea5-b970-d4af83ceb573">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T16:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:10</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>JDASEQ</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/JDASEQ/</url>
        <title>Hamnet – introduction into a wireless backbone</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We take a quick dive into the Highspeed Amateurradio Multimedia NETwork the wireless backbone of the European Amatuerradio Community. It’s uses mostly commercial hardware on it’s own frequencies beneath the 2,4 and 5 GHz wifi bands. The net is routed with it’s own ipv4 private network consisting of multiple 44.xxx.000.000/16 blocs.</abstract>
        <description>A short overview on what the Hamnet is and how it came to be. Not forgetting all the challenges of technical and legal kind that come with running and building the Net.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="135">
            <code>YXFCTE</code>
            <public_name>Lars Rokita</public_name>
            <biography>Physics student who likes to tinker around with high frequency stuff. Call DL4APT</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="358" guid="031fc5c8-09c3-5490-ad8e-3858d391763b">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T16:45:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:45</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>GWFPXV</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/GWFPXV/</url>
        <title>Observations on societal and technological changes in the DPRK</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The Democratic People's Republic of Korea (North Korea) is a hot topic in the media. The peninsula is changing rapidly, but how is that reflected in life on the ground? What is it like to live in Pyongyang? Are the externally reported societal changes and developments in technology also visible in everyday life? This talk will describe modern urban life in Pyongyang, and the recent forces driving change.</abstract>
        <description>The talk will particularly focus on observations around the state of youth mindset towards change and technology. For example, what are the future elites' attitudes towards entrepreneurship in an officially communist country? What small signals of changing attitudes can we observe that might influence the opening of the county? Presenting the realities of this environment leads us to the demo of consumer technology, and presented that opportunities for both societal change and technological development might be broader than we often see. We will present this deep dive to North Korea from the perspective of two foreigners who have been spending months at a time in Pyongyang and have been studying it since 2012.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="131">
            <code>9LVDDR</code>
            <public_name>Jukka-Pekka Heikkilä</public_name>
            <biography>A scholar, co-creator, culture hacker and entrepreneurship educator specialized in extreme settings.&#13;
&#13;
Jukka-Pekka has taught entrepreneurship courses and organized startup and science diplomacy events in Pyongyang between 2012 - 2017. He is a co-founder of WTSUP! Beirut aims to foster equality and volunteerism culture in the Middle East and a founder of Burning Stories research project that aims to study the transformation of Burning Man participants and its impact on society. From academic affiliations, Jukka-Pekka is a Newton Fellow of the Royal Society (UK) and British Academy, an Academy of Finland post-doctoral Fellow based in Aalto University, Finland, and a visiting scholar at Stanford University. In Finland, he works as a board member with The Shortcut, a sister organisation of Slush and an initiative that aims to integrate immigrants to the Finnish society via tech entrepreneurship education.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="343" guid="e0cc4db9-1ca6-5ded-a3db-1625a22f27dd">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/C33LPX/qaul-sing-blau_512_X3u9MVw.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-27T17:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:50</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>C33LPX</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/C33LPX/</url>
        <title>Refactoring qaul.net in Rust (Internet independent mesh communication App)</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Concepts, goals, implementations and the lessons learned from rewriting qaul.net decentralized messenger in rust.</abstract>
        <description>qaul.net is a Internet independent wifi mesh communication app with fully decentralized messaging, file sharing and voice chat. At the moment we are rewriting the entire application in rust, implementing our experience of 8 years off the grid peer2peer mesh communication, with a mobile first approach and a network agnostic routing protocoll wich can do synchronous as well as delay tolerant messaging. &#13;
&#13;
We are currently rewriting qaul.net 2.0 in rust with a new network agnostic routing protocol, identity based routing and delay tolerant messaging. The talk will show our learnings and the journey ahead of us at the alpha stage of the rewrite.&#13;
&#13;
* Homepage: https://qaul.net&#13;
* Code Repository: https://git.open-communication.net/qaul/qaul.net</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="120">
            <code>G78ZPE</code>
            <public_name>Mathias Jud</public_name>
            <biography>Mathias Jud is a berlin based artist. Since over twenty years, he works together with Christoph Wachter.&#13;
Their art works include open-source projects that uncover forms of censorship of the Internet, undermine the concentration of political power and even resolve the dependency on infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
https://www.wachter-jud.net/</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="361" guid="61ab92a1-92e5-56ff-9fa8-bb1156c73988">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T18:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>18:30</start>
        <duration>00:45</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>XHLTUD</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/XHLTUD/</url>
        <title>re:claimID - Self-sovereign, Decentralised Identity Management and Personal Data Sharing [YBTI/wefixthenet session]</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In this talk we present re:claimID, a decentralized, self-sovereign identity&#13;
management system. re:claimID allows users to reclaim authority over their&#13;
identities and personal data. The system is built on top if a&#13;
state-of-the-art, decentralized directory service: The GNU Name System.&#13;
Built-in cryptographic mechanisms allow users to selectively disclose&#13;
personal data and the directory service ensures that this data is accessible&#13;
to authorized parties even if the user is offline. Through OpenID Connect,&#13;
integration and use of re:claimID is straight-forward and authorization&#13;
flows are familiar. In this talk, we present the current state of re:claimID&#13;
as well as a future roadmap.</abstract>
        <description>Today, users are often required to share personal data, like email&#13;
addresses, to use services on the web. As part of normal service operation,&#13;
such as notifications or billing, services require access to -- ideally&#13;
fresh and correct -- user data. Sharing attributes in the Web today is often&#13;
done via centralized service providers to reduce data redundancy and to give&#13;
services access to current, up-to-date information even if the user is&#13;
currently offline. Abuse of this power is theoretically limited by local&#13;
laws and regulations. But, the past has shown that even well-meaning&#13;
identity providers struggle to keep user data safe as they become major&#13;
targets for hackers and nation state actors while striving for monetizing&#13;
anonymized statistics from these data. We advocate for a new, decentralized&#13;
way for users to manage their identities for the following reasons:&#13;
&#13;
*       The current state of omniscient identity providers is a significant&#13;
threat to the users' privacy.&#13;
&#13;
*       Users must completely trust the service provider with respect to&#13;
protecting the integrity and confidentiality of their identity in their&#13;
interest.&#13;
&#13;
*       The service provider itself is facing substantial liability risks&#13;
given the responsibility of securely managing potentially sensitive personal&#13;
data of millions of users.&#13;
&#13;
 &#13;
&#13;
We present re:claimID, a decentralized identity service with the following&#13;
properties:&#13;
&#13;
*       Self-sovereign: You manage your identities and attributes locally on&#13;
your computer. No need to trust a third party service with your data.&#13;
&#13;
*       Decentralized: You can share your identity attributes securely over&#13;
a decentralized name system. This allows your friends to access your shared&#13;
data without the need of a trusted third party. &#13;
&#13;
*       Standard-compliant: You can use OpenID Connect to integrate reclaim&#13;
in your web sites.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="128">
            <code>MCE83P</code>
            <public_name>dvn</public_name>
            <biography>p2p communications and privacy researcher and developer&#13;
&#13;
Currently organizing a "youbroketheinternet/wefixthenet" session at 36c3, representing GNUnet.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="370" guid="6f9aaed7-537d-50b6-a5e8-25ef1f65583d">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T20:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>20:50</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>VSV8Y8</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/VSV8Y8/</url>
        <title>SaveTheInternet - Die Urheberrechtsreform als Zündfunke demokratischer Teilhabe</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Eine kurze Erzählung von den Anfängen der Protestbewegung bis heute und darüber hinaus. Wenn eine spontan gebildete Menge an Menschen beginnt die Werkzeuge der Demokratie zu nutzen ist das vorläufige Ergebnis eine der größten Petitionen weltweit und über 200.000 kreativ Protestierende auf den Straßen Europas. War es das schon oder kommt da noch etwas? Welche Auswirkungen haben demokratische Werkzeuge wie Petitionen und Demonstrationen? Kann man die nächsten Proteste voraussehen oder wie entstehen Wellen der Aufmerksamkeit? Hat sich eine neue Empörung zum ersten oder zum letzen Mal aufgetan? Von vernetzen Livestreams während der Proteste bis zu Community Aktionen wie Meme-Events und Briefraids.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="137">
            <code>PCJYPA</code>
            <public_name>segal</public_name>
            <biography>Ich reiche Vorträge für about:freedom hier ein.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="144">
            <code>KQYUCW</code>
            <public_name>w4sserfall</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Workshop">
      <event id="367" guid="81f5f0c4-3d35-522c-8f1c-c8825b92f00a">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-27T16:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:10</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>SRMX8W</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/SRMX8W/</url>
        <title>Beginners Workshop: How to Hack your Web Application</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Did you ever want to know how hacking works? This beginners workshops gives an introduction into vulnerabilities, application pen testing and the security of web applications. Only if you know how hackers attack your application, you will be able to defend yourself. Nearly all companies use web applications nowadays. Any vulnerability in those applications may be an invitation for hackers to attack it. This workshop will give you insights on those things that you should never neglect when programming your application. From Techie to Techie!&#13;
&#13;
Requirements: programming experience &amp; laptop needed, security knowledge is not necessary</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="136">
            <code>ZWHJ7T</code>
            <public_name>Janosch Maier</public_name>
            <biography>Janosch Maier holds a computer science master degree and a pedagogy bachelor degree. He worked in several start-ups and developed a cyber security dashboard for the Dutch ministry of justice. After his studies, he founded the Crashtest Security GmbH where he develops a vulnerability scanner for web application.  Janosch is giving regular talks and workshops to promote IT security in agile software development for SMEs and corporates.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="342" guid="d979082b-5377-513a-a84b-c3f0bb3f85e2">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/NTFYAL/nachbar-und-meshnetz_DRZyVof.gif</logo>
        <date>2019-12-27T18:35:00+01:00</date>
        <start>18:35</start>
        <duration>04:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>NTFYAL</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/NTFYAL/</url>
        <title>Alpha Testing of qaul.net (Internet independent wifi mesh communication App)</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 4 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Test with us our new alpha version of the</abstract>
        <description>qaul.net is an Internet independent wifi mesh communication app with fully decentralized messaging, file sharing and voice chat. At the moment we are rewriting the entire application in rust, implementing our experience of 8 years off the grid peer2peer mesh communication, with a mobile first approach and a network agnostic routing protocoll wich can do synchronous as well as delay tolerant messaging.&#13;
&#13;
In this workshop we will test the (pre-)alpha version together, install it, test the functionality and communicate off the grid. We will explore our new routing protocol and the wireless interconnection possibilities.&#13;
&#13;
* Homepage: https://qaul.net&#13;
* Code Repository: https://git.open-communication.net/qaul/qaul.net</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="120">
            <code>G78ZPE</code>
            <public_name>Mathias Jud</public_name>
            <biography>Mathias Jud is a berlin based artist. Since over twenty years, he works together with Christoph Wachter.&#13;
Their art works include open-source projects that uncover forms of censorship of the Internet, undermine the concentration of political power and even resolve the dependency on infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
https://www.wachter-jud.net/</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day index="3" date="2019-12-28" start="2019-12-28T06:00:00+01:00" end="2019-12-29T04:00:00+01:00">
    <room name="Lecture room 11"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 14-15"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 13"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M1"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M2"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M3"/>
    <room name="Kidspace"/>
    <room name="CCL Saal 3"/>
    <room name="Chaos West Bühne"/>
    <room name="ChaosZone"/>
    <room name="OIO Stage">
      <event id="371" guid="2b1e7aea-237f-533a-8e7b-022a81ba81dc">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T12:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>12:00</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>E77J8R</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/E77J8R/</url>
        <title>Ubuntu Touch &amp; Co - GNU/Linux in der Hosentasche</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Der Markt für Mobilgeräte wird dominiert von Android und der Anteil freier Komponenten wird merklich kleiner. Einige Projekte versuchen das zu ändern und bringen GNU/Linux auf Handies und Tablets zu bringen. Wir schauen uns verschiedene solche Projekte an und sprechen über die Notwendigkeit, den aktuellen Stand und die Zukunftsaussichten von GNU/Linux auf Mobilgeräten. Am Beispiel von Ubuntu Touch gehen wir auf besondere Herausforderungen ein.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="137">
            <code>PCJYPA</code>
            <public_name>segal</public_name>
            <biography>Ich reiche Vorträge für about:freedom hier ein.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="145">
            <code>ESUXA7</code>
            <public_name>Jan Sprinz</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="374" guid="2264aaad-2df6-545f-918c-cc5caea4e507">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T12:40:00+01:00</date>
        <start>12:40</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>3JU7Y9</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/3JU7Y9/</url>
        <title>Building Nextcloud Flow</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Nextcloud Flow is the overhauled workflow engine in upcoming Nextcloud 18. This talk describes how it evolved, how it works internally, and especially how own components can be built, so you can set up automatized tasks  in your Nextcloud.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="138">
            <code>KYJPPS</code>
            <public_name>Blizzz</public_name>
            <biography>I am a father and Nextcloud developer.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="359" guid="98591fc6-852a-5251-bba5-12436614c1f3">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/BJQTYA/avatar1_cqxI94G.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-28T13:45:00+01:00</date>
        <start>13:45</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>BJQTYA</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/BJQTYA/</url>
        <title>Exploring and empowering participatory culture communities with the use of online ethnography platform</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We explore the potential of scalable online ethnography to study the rapidly growing phenomenon of participatory culture communities and discuss the potential benefits and challenges of using an online platform in hacker communities. The presentation shares views, with a demo, on how to build participatory online communities from a pilot that focused on the global Burning Man community.</abstract>
        <description>The talk is grounded on the collaboration of two high-impact research projects, Burning Stories and Edgeryders. Firstly the aim of Burning Stories, by combining science and arts, is to study the global Burning Man community and seek to explain the processes through which community membership of Burning Man participants evolves across time and space, and how this, in turn, affects the society. By combining the Burning Stories research project with an online ethnography tool from Edgeryders, who use it for multiple Horizon 2020 funded project, the talk aims to present novel ways of disrupting the traditional ways of conducting ethnography in order to understand the emergence of a new cultural phenomenon and apply new, participatory methodology, in order to advance social sciences and community building. The presentation particularly focuses on lessons learnt from these two research projects and with the combination of the projects, explores the potential future use of the co-creative templates for hacker communities.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="131">
            <code>9LVDDR</code>
            <public_name>Jukka-Pekka Heikkilä</public_name>
            <biography>A scholar, co-creator, culture hacker and entrepreneurship educator specialized in extreme settings.&#13;
&#13;
Jukka-Pekka has taught entrepreneurship courses and organized startup and science diplomacy events in Pyongyang between 2012 - 2017. He is a co-founder of WTSUP! Beirut aims to foster equality and volunteerism culture in the Middle East and a founder of Burning Stories research project that aims to study the transformation of Burning Man participants and its impact on society. From academic affiliations, Jukka-Pekka is a Newton Fellow of the Royal Society (UK) and British Academy, an Academy of Finland post-doctoral Fellow based in Aalto University, Finland, and a visiting scholar at Stanford University. In Finland, he works as a board member with The Shortcut, a sister organisation of Slush and an initiative that aims to integrate immigrants to the Finnish society via tech entrepreneurship education.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="368" guid="83e0c501-6a60-555f-80af-36b22a440fd4">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T14:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>14:30</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>EW8MBQ</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/EW8MBQ/</url>
        <title>NPR70 - "WLAN" auf 430MHz</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Da A.25 mit 9k6 baud irgend wann einfach nicht mehr cool ist um Daten auf 430 Mhz zu übertragen, musste ein neues Protokoll mit passender Hardware her. Herausgekommen ist ein open source Projekt von F4HDK mit 500kbit/s nutzdaten, multiuser und schnellen Rundlaufzeiten.</abstract>
        <description>Nachdem das nötige Hintergrundswissen zu dem Thema Drahtlose Übertragungsprotokolle vermittelt wurde. Wird das Protokoll und die dazugehörende Hardware ausführlich vorgestellt und mit alternativen wie z.B. LORA verglichen.&#13;
Außerdem soll rund um den OIO im laufe des Kongresses ein Demo-Netzwerk aufgebaut werden hierfür können auch noch Kits vorort gelötet werden, meldet euch dafür einfach bei mir.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="135">
            <code>YXFCTE</code>
            <public_name>Lars Rokita</public_name>
            <biography>Physics student who likes to tinker around with high frequency stuff. Call DL4APT</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="366" guid="cface55d-a792-55e0-9eda-d2e4a72b43fb">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T16:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:10</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>G3LD3P</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/G3LD3P/</url>
        <title>FF-ESP32-OpenMPPT - New Freifunk-ISEMS-MPPT-Solar-Controller with integrated WiFi</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The Independent Solar Mesh System has a new hardware that will bring the power consumption, space and cost requirements of low cost WiFi relay stations down: FF-ESP32-.OpenMPPT</abstract>
        <description>In order to build the cheapest energy autonomous WiFi relay possible, we have designed an update to the previous Freifunk-Open-MPPT-Solarcontroller. It has now integrated WiFi and Bluetooth, so it doesn't need an external WiFi router anymore, but you can still connect one. Technical data is preliminary at the moment, but power consumption will be between ~0.3 at low load and ~0.6 Watt at maximum load. So a 20 Watt Solar panel and a 12V 7Ah battery will be more than enough to keep the system running and relaying traffic all year.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="57">
            <code>HZ9WHF</code>
            <public_name>Elektra Wagenrad</public_name>
            <biography>FF-Activist since 2003.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="373" guid="d84a392d-0680-584c-8a35-358977418a13">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T16:45:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:45</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>A8GQTE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/A8GQTE/</url>
        <title>“Computer says no”: Worüber sollen Algorithmen entscheiden dürfen</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Richtlinien für den ethischen Einsatz von Algorithmen gibt es langsam wirklich genug. Konzerne und Organisationen    übertrumpfen sich geradezu damit zu betonen, dass der Mensch bei allen maschinellen Entscheidungen im Mittelpunkt stehen soll, dass die Systeme fair und nachvollziehbar arbeiten müssen. Aber egal, ob sie nun direkt von Google und IBM stammen, von Normungsorganisationen wie IEEE oder der OECD – gemeinsam ist all diesen Richtlinien: Sie sind rechtlich nicht bindend. Die Frage ist also: Wem dienen solche Ansätze der unternehmerischen und    staatlichen Selbstregulierung? Und wollen wir uns auf sie verlassen oder brauchen wir klare gesetzliche Auflagen? Welche Regeln sollten für Unternehmen gelten, welche für den Staat? Und wer soll darüber wachen, dass sie eingehalten werden?</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="137">
            <code>PCJYPA</code>
            <public_name>segal</public_name>
            <biography>Ich reiche Vorträge für about:freedom hier ein.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="142">
            <code>AWJ9RX</code>
            <public_name>Chris Köver</public_name>
            <biography>.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="382" guid="35cda8cc-6647-5a55-b87f-2e65057ef9e5">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T17:15:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:15</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>P9BACD</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/P9BACD/</url>
        <title>Freifunk Super Node und Firmware Build Server aufsetzen und Provider werden</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Ein howto für Dummis, Freifunk Infrastruktur selber zu betreiben.</abstract>
        <description>Es ist gut, wenn viele Menschen Freifunk Router einrichten können. Doch es ist besser, wenn auch Leute selber einen Super Node betreiben können. Es gibt viele Wege, dies umzusetzen. Ich möchte zeigen, wie ich in letzter Zeit es umgesetzt habe mit mittleren Kenntnissen. Und es wird gezeigt, wie man Provider werden kann.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="42">
            <code>JGBAWZ</code>
            <public_name>Matthias Schmidt</public_name>
            <biography>1996 mit 16 Jahren habe ich erste Netzwerk Erfahrungen gesammelt, ab dem Jahr 2000 bin ich im Internet. Seit 2014 mache ich bei Freifunk Düren und Aachen mit. Ich bin Mitglied beim Freifunk Rheinland e.V. und Fördervereinigung freier Netzwerke in der Region Aachen e.V., beim F3N bin ich Beisitzer. Seit wenigen Monaten betreibe ich einen eigenen Super Node auf einer Test Infrasruktur. Bei der Bundesnetzagentur bin ich als "datendurchleitend" deklariert. Der nächste Schritt möge sein, von einem LIR einen IP Block zu bekommen.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="360" guid="9ca25e43-bcd8-541c-b79c-bfb6db1c2789">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/8D7DBP/logos_to_replace_78tfwYe.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-28T18:15:00+01:00</date>
        <start>18:15</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>8D7DBP</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/8D7DBP/</url>
        <title>A dozen more things you didn't know Nextcloud could do</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>With Nextcloud you can sync, share and collaborate on data, but you don't need to put your photos, calendars or chat logs on an American server. Nope, Nextcloud is self-hosted and 100% open source! Thanks to hundreds of apps, Nextcloud can do a lot and in this talk, I will highlight some cool things.</abstract>
        <description>Consider this a follow-up from my talk about 200 things Nextcloud can do last year! An update on what's new and some cool new stuff. What, what is `Nextcloud`? Let's see. A private cloud is one way to put it, though that's a contradiction of course. It is a way to share your data, sync your files, communicate and collaborate with others - without giving your data to GAFAM! Keep it on your own server, or something close (like a local hosting provider or data center). Nextcloud is a PHP app that does all that, and more! Easy to use, secure (really) and fully open source of course.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="59">
            <code>KMKHUZ</code>
            <public_name>Jos Poortvliet</public_name>
            <biography>People person, technology enthusiast and all-things-open evangelist. Head of marketing at Nextcloud, previously Community Manager at ownCloud and SUSE, recovering business consultant with decade long involvement in the KDE community. Enjoys avoiding traffic and public transport on bike through Berlin, but only when the weather is good. Loves cooking for friends and family and playing with the dog.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="369" guid="aa7b077e-6de3-5bbf-aefd-1e6da636adbf">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T20:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>20:50</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>LU3JNL</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/LU3JNL/</url>
        <title>Extending the lifetime of smartphones with Replicant, a fully free Android distribution</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>After a very quick introduction on Replicant and the smartphones ecosystem, we will look at what affects smartphones' and tablets' lifetime and how to increase it by making Replicant more sustainable.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="137">
            <code>PCJYPA</code>
            <public_name>segal</public_name>
            <biography>Ich reiche Vorträge für about:freedom hier ein.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="143">
            <code>VLPGUU</code>
            <public_name>Denis 'GNUtoo' Carikli</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="362" guid="4b6379f9-a6d9-5c3e-8af9-a9c1b1c04e95">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/GUZH7V/logo_GGS6DxK.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-28T21:20:00+01:00</date>
        <start>21:20</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>GUZH7V</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/GUZH7V/</url>
        <title>CloudCalypse 2: Social network with net2o [YBTI/wefixthenet session]</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Building a social network on top of net2o, and importing your existing data</abstract>
        <description>I've a dream: A peer-to-peer network, where services like search engines or social networks aren't offered by big companies, who in turn need to make money by selling the privacy of their users. Where all data is encrypted, so that access is only possible for people who have the key and really are authorized. Which layman can use without cryptic user interfaces. Where the browser is a platform for running useful applications without the mess of Flash and JavaScript. Without the lag of “buffer bloat” and without the speed problems of a protocol not designed to be assisted by hardware.&#13;
&#13;
This dream is coming to reality: This talk will show how far I got, and what challenges still are ahead. The talk is in three parts:&#13;
&#13;
1. a short overview over net2o&#13;
2. a demonstration of how the social network stuff looks like&#13;
3. and an outlook over what needs to be done to make it a polished product</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="128">
            <code>MCE83P</code>
            <public_name>dvn</public_name>
            <biography>p2p communications and privacy researcher and developer&#13;
&#13;
Currently organizing a "youbroketheinternet/wefixthenet" session at 36c3, representing GNUnet.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="132">
            <code>SP93BA</code>
            <public_name>Bernd Paysan</public_name>
            <biography>I'm the GNU Forth maintainer and the principal developer of net2o, a complete alternative network stack that runs as overlay on UDP.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="383" guid="18ce862e-36e1-5df6-803b-38f82b2ef327">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T22:25:00+01:00</date>
        <start>22:25</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>L7MBH8</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/L7MBH8/</url>
        <title>WiFi-Hostpot-Abos - Wie viel Freifunk steckt drin?</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Im Internet offerieren diverse Anbieter WiFi Hardware inklusive VPN für 10€.&#13;
&#13;
Dieser Talk behandelt, wie sehr sich die verkaufte Hardware sowie Software von den meisten Freifunk Setups unterscheidet.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="140">
            <code>DGCAVP</code>
            <public_name>blocktrron</public_name>
            <biography>Working on Freifunk / Gluon / OpenWrt.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Workshop">
      <event id="347" guid="bf48fa55-92a1-5481-a14a-f77cc0d4fccb">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T11:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>11:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>FU3ZZE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/FU3ZZE/</url>
        <title>Nudeln hacken - Wettbewerb für Junghacker von 5 Jahren bis ∞</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 1 hour</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Spaß am Gerät: Mehrere Teams bauen gleichzeitig mit Nudeln um die Wette. Dabei geht es um kreativen Umgang mit Technik und die Erfahrung, dass man Dinge auch jenseits der eigentlichen Verwendungszwecke gut gebrauchen kann. Junghacker bzw. solche die es werden wollen, können alleine oder als Team kommen. Es kann jeder mitmachen, der weiß, was eine Nudel ist. PS: Es werden keine Lebensmittel verschwendet. PPS: Erwachsene dürfen auch mitmachen, wenn sie den Junghacker keinen Platz wegnehmen. Sie werden aber wahrscheinlich gegen den Nachwuchs verlieren :-D</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>true</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="74">
            <code>73PEWU</code>
            <public_name>Stefan Safari</public_name>
            <biography>Ich arbeite sehr gerne mit Gruppen, mag den kreativen Umgang mit Dingen und liebe es, gutes Essen zu essen.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="348" guid="c4bd3614-30a5-5739-a7f6-6880be23709b">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T13:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>13:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>RW3HCE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/RW3HCE/</url>
        <title>Trotz Schule die Zukunft meistern? - Mitmach-Workshop für Menschen von 10-100 Jahre</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 1 hour</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In einem Workshop überlegen Schüler*innen gemeinsam mit anderen, wie man sich auf Berufe vorbereitet, die es heute noch gar nicht gibt. Und warum das eigene Smartphone- und Social-Media-Verhalten einem die Zukunft rettet statt sie zu vergeigen.</abstract>
        <description>Die Schüler*innen von heute werden später Jobs machen, von denen es 65% heute noch gar nicht gibt - sagt eine Studie, der OECD. Die OECD hat auch Thesen aufgestellt worauf es in der Zukunft ankommt. Da werden Punkte wie "Problem lösen/kritisches Denken" oder "Kreativität" genannt und persönliche Eigentschaften wie "Neugierde", "Initiative" oder "Ausdauer/Entschlossenheit" aufgelistet. Bereitet einen die Schule wirklich auf so was vor, oder sind die Lernwelten nicht viel größer. Wie ist ein Besuch des 36C3 einzuordnen? Wie "wird man neugierig"?&#13;
&#13;
Der Workshop wird besonders lebendig, wenn verschiedene Altergruppen/ Generationen teilnehmen. Wenn es allerdings eng im Raum wird, werden Schüler*innen bevorzugt.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>true</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="74">
            <code>73PEWU</code>
            <public_name>Stefan Safari</public_name>
            <biography>Ich arbeite sehr gerne mit Gruppen, mag den kreativen Umgang mit Dingen und liebe es, gutes Essen zu essen.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="347" guid="bf48fa55-92a1-5481-a14a-f77cc0d4fccb">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T15:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>15:30</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>FU3ZZE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/FU3ZZE/</url>
        <title>Nudeln hacken - Wettbewerb für Junghacker von 5 Jahren bis ∞</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 1 hour</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Spaß am Gerät: Mehrere Teams bauen gleichzeitig mit Nudeln um die Wette. Dabei geht es um kreativen Umgang mit Technik und die Erfahrung, dass man Dinge auch jenseits der eigentlichen Verwendungszwecke gut gebrauchen kann. Junghacker bzw. solche die es werden wollen, können alleine oder als Team kommen. Es kann jeder mitmachen, der weiß, was eine Nudel ist. PS: Es werden keine Lebensmittel verschwendet. PPS: Erwachsene dürfen auch mitmachen, wenn sie den Junghacker keinen Platz wegnehmen. Sie werden aber wahrscheinlich gegen den Nachwuchs verlieren :-D</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>true</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="74">
            <code>73PEWU</code>
            <public_name>Stefan Safari</public_name>
            <biography>Ich arbeite sehr gerne mit Gruppen, mag den kreativen Umgang mit Dingen und liebe es, gutes Essen zu essen.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="375" guid="5634bc77-b6ad-52ae-88c5-c059cfcebb8e">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T18:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>18:00</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>TZBSSE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/TZBSSE/</url>
        <title>SDR kennenlernen</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Software Defined Radios in Kombination mit open source tools erlauben es einfach anspruchsvolle aufgeben umzusetzen. Nach einer kurzen theoretischen Engführung kann sich jeder an verschieden Beispielen versuchen Signale zu empfangen und zu dekodiren.</abstract>
        <description>Vom FM Radio bis hin zu z.B. Wlan frames wollen wir uns verscheide Dinge anschauen. Wer es kann bitte einen Laptop mitbringen um eigenständig arbeiten zu können. English speakers can also attend but may have to wait a bit for there instructions.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="135">
            <code>YXFCTE</code>
            <public_name>Lars Rokita</public_name>
            <biography>Physics student who likes to tinker around with high frequency stuff. Call DL4APT</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="353" guid="c05054ed-aca8-5d2f-814c-0d6e8851d96e">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/CTQSQ8/meetup_1920_7FtptxA.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-28T20:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>20:30</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>CTQSQ8</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/CTQSQ8/</url>
        <title>Open Communication Meetup! - Decentralized Social Networks</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We will test, discuss and document decentralized and off the grid social networks, such as secure scuttlebutt SSCB.</abstract>
        <description>The goal behind [open-communication.net](https://open-communication.net) is to build a knowledge base on open decentralized communication tools. This is done collectively and collaboratively in 'Open Communication Meetups'.&#13;
&#13;
In this meetup we will test, discuss and document existing decentralized and off-the-grid social networks, such as [secure scuttlebutt](https://scuttlebutt.nz/). &#13;
&#13;
Please bring your laptops and digital devices in order to collectively test the projects!&#13;
&#13;
https://open-communication.net</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="120">
            <code>G78ZPE</code>
            <public_name>Mathias Jud</public_name>
            <biography>Mathias Jud is a berlin based artist. Since over twenty years, he works together with Christoph Wachter.&#13;
Their art works include open-source projects that uncover forms of censorship of the Internet, undermine the concentration of political power and even resolve the dependency on infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
https://www.wachter-jud.net/</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="ChaosZone Workshop">
      <event id="735" guid="4041ab59-5add-5f84-9a37-d716c468a136">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-28T10:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>10:00</start>
        <duration>08:00</duration>
        <room>ChaosZone Workshop</room>
        <slug>PU7RSW</slug>
        <url>https://cfp.chaoszone.cz/36c3/talk/PU7RSW/</url>
        <title>Junghackertag</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 8h</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Der Junghackertag der Chaoszone ist Teil des 36C3-Junghackertages am 28.12.  (link zum 36C3 Junghackertag, wenn verfügbar)</abstract>
        <description>Es gibt verschiedene Stationen, bei denen Du Dich ausprobieren kannst: &#13;
- Du kannst Lötkits löten, einfache Buttons bis komplexe Laufschrift-Namensschilder, Du suchst es Dir aus.&#13;
- Es gibt mBot Roboterautos, die Du steuern kannst.&#13;
- Du kannst auch vorher mit einem Programm arbeiten und dabei ausprobieren, wie so eine Steuerung funktioniert.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="35">
            <code>LTF3B7</code>
            <public_name>r2d2data</public_name>
            <biography>Bin in Verein dezentrale</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="49">
            <code>PGSUMT</code>
            <public_name>rezzisto</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day index="4" date="2019-12-29" start="2019-12-29T06:00:00+01:00" end="2019-12-30T04:00:00+01:00">
    <room name="Lecture room 11"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 14-15"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 13"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M1"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M2"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M3"/>
    <room name="Kidspace"/>
    <room name="CCL Saal 3"/>
    <room name="Chaos West Bühne"/>
    <room name="ChaosZone"/>
    <room name="OIO Stage">
      <event id="363" guid="a3f9136b-fa32-504d-a762-438d5141ac74">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T16:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:10</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>VPUTHL</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/VPUTHL/</url>
        <title>Treating IS - Humanitäre Prinzipien im Konflikt</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Frank Dörner von Ärzte ohne Grenzen und Sebastian Jünemann von CADUS diskutieren die jüngsten Angriffe auf humanitäre Prinzipien in verschiedenen Kontexten, wie beispielsweise während der medizinischen Nothilfe in Nordost-Syrien.</abstract>
        <description>Eigentlich sollte es klar sein: Menschen die medizinische Hilfe benötigen sollen sie auch bekommen, Punkt. Doch in Medienkommentaren wird der humanitären Hilfsorganisation CADUS, die ein Feldkrankenhaus im Camp Al Hol in Nordost-Syrien betreibt, längst nicht nur Respekt ausgesprochen. Manche Kommentator*innen schlagen vor, humanitäre Prinzipien auszusetzen sobald es sich bei den Hilfesuchenden um mutmaßliche Angehörige des sogenannten Islamischen Staates (IS) handelt. Schließlich, so die Argumentation, missachte diese Organisation systematisch eben solche Prinzipien. &#13;
&#13;
In vielen Konflikten werden humanitäre Grundsätze heute zunehmend missachtet. Helfende werden zu Feinden erklärt und damit legitime Ziele für jedwede Aggression. Krankenhäuser und Ambulanzen können gezielt angegriffen werden, ohne dass es Konsequenzen hat. Afghanistan, Syrien, Yemen – die Liste ist lang. Und aus der jüngsten Geschichte der Seenotrettung wissen wir: auch von staatlichen Stellen werden immer wieder humanitäre Grundsätze mit Füßen getreten. &#13;
&#13;
Frank Dörner von Ärzte ohne Grenzen und Sebastian Jünemann von CADUS geben einen Einblick was es bedeutet, in gesellschaftlich und politisch stark umstrittenen Kontexten Hilfe zu leisten, in denen humanitäre Prinzipien immer wieder aus verschiedensten Richtungen angegriffen werden.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="133">
            <code>M7YNCY</code>
            <public_name>Sebastian Jünemann</public_name>
            <biography>Gründer der unabhängigen humanitären Hilfsorganisation CADUS e.V., die in Zusammenarbeit mit lokalen Partner*innen medizinische und technische Nothilfe leistet. CADUS ist hauptsächlich in Nordost-Syrien und im Nord-Irak tätig. Im Berliner Crisis Response Makerspace der Organisation werden open source Lösungen für Herausforderungen in der humanitären Hilfe entwickelt.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="150">
            <code>ADFHYV</code>
            <public_name>Frank Dörner</public_name>
            <biography>Frank Dörner ist Allgemeinarzt und arbeitet seit Ende der 90er im humanitären Kontext mit Ärzte ohne Grenzen. Er hat in verschiedensten Projekten gearbeitet und war 6 Jahre lang Geschäftsführer in Berlin. Frank gehört zum Gründungskreis von Sea-Watch und war mehrfach im Einsatz auf dem Meer, letztmalig im Januar 2019. Seit Mai diesen Jahres gehört Frank zudem zum Vorstand von ÄoG.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="384" guid="d7287f76-3369-5017-89f7-35101cc72a18">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T17:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:10</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>UYCLAE</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/UYCLAE/</url>
        <title>Hacking health</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>About hacking wheelchairs, building custom bicycles, adapters to use e-scooters as outboard motors: Empowering people with disablitities or healthcare needs through Open Hardware. Presentation on experiences and lessons learned in collecting and co-creating open personalized DIY healthcare solutions for replicability and adaptability in Makerspace worldwide.</abstract>
        <description>Careables are open source solutions that aim to improve the quality of life for people with unmet particular needs or facing physical limitations. Careables are often co-designed, replicable, accessible, adjustable and shareable online using digital technologies.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="96">
            <code>P3GLDY</code>
            <public_name>Sandra GIG</public_name>
            <biography>Sandra Mamitzsch baut seit 2018 das Berliner Büro des Global Innovation Gathering e.V., einem globalen Netzwerk von Makern und Innovatoren, auf und beschäftigt sich daher viel damit, wie dezentrale Zusammenarbeit und offene Organisationsformen funktionieren. Hauptsächlich ist sie im Verein für das Horizon2020-Förderprojekt Careables.org verantwortlich, dass innerhalb von Makerspace-Communities dabei hilft, mit offenen Technologien und Co-Design in Gesundheit und Pflege das Leben von Menschen zu verbessern. Von 2012-2017 war sie Programmdirektorin der re:publica und arbeitet dort weiterhin als freie Beraterin und Kuratorin. Nebenbei ist sie Mitglied bei European Digital Rights (EDRi) und beim Digitale Gesellschaft e.V.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="354" guid="18a492b2-6219-5b95-a48d-b03944b75739">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T17:40:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:40</start>
        <duration>00:45</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>WSLWVM</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/WSLWVM/</url>
        <title>Delta Chat: e-mail based messaging, the Rustocalypse and UX driven approach [YBTI/wefixthenet session]</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Delta Chat is an e-mail instant messenger that is just becoming available on all platforms. &#13;
Unlike other offerings, Delta Chat is no platform and operates no own servers. &#13;
Instead it uses existing SMTP/IMAP servers to send and receive messages.&#13;
We'll talk about the current development status on all platforms, our new &#13;
Rust-core based approach, our decentralized e2e-encryption facilities (not requiring &#13;
keyservers, and safe against active attacks) and how we are generally driving&#13;
developments from UX and security perspectives.  We also aim to showcase&#13;
"burner accounts", a new concept that we are developing and discussing&#13;
with activists in eastern european countries and asian cities.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="128">
            <code>MCE83P</code>
            <public_name>dvn</public_name>
            <biography>p2p communications and privacy researcher and developer&#13;
&#13;
Currently organizing a "youbroketheinternet/wefixthenet" session at 36c3, representing GNUnet.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="388" guid="81b0de17-dbef-5da7-80e8-4d9ae563a4fd">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T19:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>19:00</start>
        <duration>00:45</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>MPCRC8</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/MPCRC8/</url>
        <title>Freifunk und die Haftungsprivilegierung des Telemediengesetzes</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Seit Jahren kämpfen wir um die Haftungsprivilegierung für Freifunker. Als Zugangsvermittler in das Internet hat der Gesetzgeber den Freifunker als Diensteanbieter von Ansprüchen Dritter freigestellt. Nach dem Gesetz ist der Freifunker für die Handlungen Dritter im Internet nicht verantwortlich. Wie die Rechtssprechung die gesetzliche Regelung anwendet, möchte ich Euch in meinem Vortrag berichten.</abstract>
        <description>Ich würde gerne den Vortrag in meinen Bericht über die einzelnen Freifunk-Verfahren gegen die Rechteinhaber einbetten. Ich weiß noch nicht recht, wie ich den Zusammenhang gestalte. Mit wem könnte ich darüber sprechen?</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="75">
            <code>UEK7FN</code>
            <public_name>Beata Hubrig</public_name>
            <biography>Mit Anfang zwanzig entschied ich mich, Rechtsanwältin zu werden und habe immer wieder große Freude daran, die zivilrechtlichen Interessen im Urheberrecht und Datenschutz zu vertreten. Dabei lege ich großen Wert auf die Durchsetzung des generellen Zugangs zu Informationen und wissenschaftlichen Werken sowie auf den Schutz jeder natürlichen Person vor dem Missbrauch ihrer personenbezogenen Daten.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="357" guid="35f647fc-1849-5194-a354-2e855e7a642d">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/SHDVXB/t1-engine_pvMnznO.jpg</logo>
        <date>2019-12-29T21:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>21:30</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>SHDVXB</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/SHDVXB/</url>
        <title>Raumfahrtantriebe</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Wie kommt man eigentlich in den Weltraum und was ist an so ein bisschen Schub so kompliziert *?&#13;
&#13;
Warum sehen Raumfahrtantriebe so aus wie sie sind und was wird sich mit "New Space" alles ändern?&#13;
&#13;
&#13;
(*)insert rocket science joke here</abstract>
        <description>Preview&#13;
1. Wie erzeugt man Schub?&#13;
-	Was ist eine Raketenmotor -triebwerk?&#13;
-	Warum fliegen Flaschenraketen mit Wasser höher?&#13;
&#13;
2. Feststoffraketen&#13;
-	Feuerwerk, Modellbau oder Shuttle Booster&#13;
-	Brennprofile&#13;
&#13;
3. Flüssigraketen&#13;
-	Goddards erste Versuche&#13;
-	Komplex, teuer, fehleranfällig und warum wir trotzdem Flüssigtreibstoffe nutzen&#13;
3.1. Brennkammer&#13;
-	Aufbau und Eigenschaften&#13;
3.2. Turbopumpen&#13;
-	Wie kommt der Treibstoff und Oxidator in die Brennkammer&#13;
3.3. Düsen&#13;
-	warum überhaupt Düsen und warum sehen sie so aus wie sie sind&#13;
-	Aerospike&#13;
3.4. Treibstoffe&#13;
-	Ein wenig Chemie.  Mono-, Bi- und Tritreibstoff &#13;
3.5. 5,4 all engines running,2,1,0 lift off&#13;
-	Wie man eine Rakete startet Soyuz, Titan II, Delta 4 und das Space-Shuttle&#13;
4. Hybridraketen&#13;
-	Die Komplexität einer Flüssigrakete mit den Nachteilen einer Feststoffrakete&#13;
5. Ionenantrieb&#13;
-	Wenig Schub aber hoher Impuls &#13;
-	Aufbau und Eigenschaften&#13;
6. Solar Sail&#13;
-	Ein Segel spannen und mit dem Sonnenwind dahingleiten&#13;
7. Nuklearantriebe&#13;
-	Ein fliegender Kernreaktor, was kann da schon schief gehen?&#13;
-	in 200 Tagen zum Mars und zurück</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="127">
            <code>H3NCWF</code>
            <public_name>Äpex</public_name>
            <biography>armchair rocket scientists.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="381" guid="03d76db0-ea48-516b-94f2-b731cccf47de">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T22:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>22:00</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>7WUGHV</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/7WUGHV/</url>
        <title>Ethische Grenzen im Making</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Machbarkeit im Making wird vornehmlich von physikalischen Gesetzen bestimmt. Doch wie sieht es mit ethischen Grenzen aus? Vor allem im Gesundheitsbereich stellt sich die Frage, ob alles das was reverse engineered und selbst gebaut werden kann tatsächlich auch von der maker community diesem Prozess unterzogen werden sollte. Über diese Frage diskutieren Steini und Seb (CADUS).</abstract>
        <description>„Tut mir leid, alle von offiziellen Stellen geprüften und zertifizierten Medizingeräte sind kaputt, aber wir überwachen Sie während der OP einfach mit diesem selbst zusammengebauten open source Patienten-Monitor, kein Problem.“&#13;
&#13;
Machbarkeit im Making wird vornehmlich von physikalischen Gesetzen bestimmt. Doch wie sieht es mit ethischen Grenzen aus? Vor allem im Gesundheitsbereich stellt sich die Frage, ob alles das was reverse engineered und selbst gebaut werden kann tatsächlich auch von der maker community diesem Prozess unterzogen werden sollte. Über diese Frage diskutieren Steini und Seb (CADUS).</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="133">
            <code>M7YNCY</code>
            <public_name>Sebastian Jünemann</public_name>
            <biography>Gründer der unabhängigen humanitären Hilfsorganisation CADUS e.V., die in Zusammenarbeit mit lokalen Partner*innen medizinische und technische Nothilfe leistet. CADUS ist hauptsächlich in Nordost-Syrien und im Nord-Irak tätig. Im Berliner Crisis Response Makerspace der Organisation werden open source Lösungen für Herausforderungen in der humanitären Hilfe entwickelt.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="149">
            <code>AT7TJC</code>
            <public_name>Steini</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Workshop">
      <event id="344" guid="312560c7-7ce7-5c81-97b4-7692b2d9a240">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/HHZQAY/meetup_1920_ssHGXLa.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-29T13:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>13:50</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>HHZQAY</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/HHZQAY/</url>
        <title>Open Communication Meetup! - Adhoc mesh routing protocols</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We will discuss and document mobile ad-hoc mesh routing protocols.</abstract>
        <description>The goal behind [open-communication.net](https://open-communication.net) is to build a knowledge base on open decentralized communication tools. This is done collectively and collaboratively in 'Open Communication Meetups'.&#13;
&#13;
In this meetup we will discuss and document existing open and decentralized mesh routing protocols. &#13;
&#13;
https://open-communication.net</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="120">
            <code>G78ZPE</code>
            <public_name>Mathias Jud</public_name>
            <biography>Mathias Jud is a berlin based artist. Since over twenty years, he works together with Christoph Wachter.&#13;
Their art works include open-source projects that uncover forms of censorship of the Internet, undermine the concentration of political power and even resolve the dependency on infrastructure.&#13;
&#13;
https://www.wachter-jud.net/</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="349" guid="c8793eb8-53be-5a90-b549-f5789da4d174">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/PATB9E/lynXified-amirouche-anonymous-v3_C4S2fqs.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-29T16:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>16:00</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>PATB9E</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/PATB9E/</url>
        <title>GNUnet e.V. annual assembly</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 1 hour</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>https://gnunet.org/ e.V. annually meets to discuss all things GNUnet e.V.-related (including finances, elections, and community update). The full agenda will be determined closer to the event.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="123">
            <code>JXPKXS</code>
            <public_name>Christian Grothoff</public_name>
            <biography>https://grothoff.org/christian/</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="355" guid="6d1b8adb-0f77-5693-a768-fabf2c252929">
        <logo>/media/36c3-oio/images/VHZQKJ/LoRaWAN5_apfiK6P.png</logo>
        <date>2019-12-29T17:10:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:10</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>VHZQKJ</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/VHZQKJ/</url>
        <title>Getting started connecting your Devices using LoRaWAN</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>LoRaWAN is a **Lo**ng **Ra**nge **W**ide **A**rea **N**etwork that can connect devices over several kilometres while operating on very low power. It uses freely available frequencies, and with successful community project *The Things Network* there exists an open and free network. This makes LoRaWAN ideal for that small gadgets you want to deploy out in the field and also really interesting for a hacker community. Let's get working on it!</abstract>
        <description>We will be going through the whole process of how to build, program, and setup a simple LoRaWAN connected device using an *Arduino* and *The Things Network*. The workshop will start with an introduction to how LoRaWAN works, but the session is planed to be a more interactive format where we get a bit of work done together.&#13;
&#13;
If you need an introduction, why LoRaWAN is interesting, you can watch our 20min talk from last year: &lt;br&gt;&#13;
https://media.ccc.de/v/35c3chaoswest-27-long-range-radio-communication-for-everyone-using-lorawan-&#13;
&#13;
If you want to know how you can come prepared, go to: &lt;br&gt;&#13;
https://www.deepcyber.de/36c3/lorawan</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="129">
            <code>YRX8PJ</code>
            <public_name>Peer Springstübe</public_name>
            <biography>Have done my Diploma in Informatik (that's *Computer Science* in Germany) and got a side order of Physics and Philosophy with it. Tried out robotics and deep learning while at university. I am now working with a company that does industrial IoT focused on NB-IoT and LoRaWAN. &#13;
&#13;
I am heavily involved with [deep cyber](https://www.deepcyber.de) &amp;ndash; check out our assembly at 36c3!</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="385" guid="f3e731fa-1a62-5238-969a-7f28e5812334">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-29T20:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>20:50</start>
        <duration>01:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>8PGUXK</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/8PGUXK/</url>
        <title>Global Innovation Gathering meetup</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 1 hour</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The Global Innovation Gathering (GIG) is a diverse community of innovation hubs, makerspaces, hackerspaces and other grassroot innovation community spaces and initiatives as well as individual innovators, makers, technologists and changemakers.&#13;
&#13;
With strong roots in the global south, we share, collaborate and work together globally. GIG provides a platform for meaningful exchange by fostering knowledge exchange and collaboration between its members. We have a non-profit organisation registered in Germany.&#13;
&#13;
GIG is pursuing a new vision for global cooperation based on equality, openness and sharing. We aim to enable more diversity in the production of technology, and global innovation processes and support open and sustainable solutions developed by grassroot innovators.&#13;
&#13;
What can we create together?</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="96">
            <code>P3GLDY</code>
            <public_name>Sandra GIG</public_name>
            <biography>Sandra Mamitzsch baut seit 2018 das Berliner Büro des Global Innovation Gathering e.V., einem globalen Netzwerk von Makern und Innovatoren, auf und beschäftigt sich daher viel damit, wie dezentrale Zusammenarbeit und offene Organisationsformen funktionieren. Hauptsächlich ist sie im Verein für das Horizon2020-Förderprojekt Careables.org verantwortlich, dass innerhalb von Makerspace-Communities dabei hilft, mit offenen Technologien und Co-Design in Gesundheit und Pflege das Leben von Menschen zu verbessern. Von 2012-2017 war sie Programmdirektorin der re:publica und arbeitet dort weiterhin als freie Beraterin und Kuratorin. Nebenbei ist sie Mitglied bei European Digital Rights (EDRi) und beim Digitale Gesellschaft e.V.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
  <day index="5" date="2019-12-30" start="2019-12-30T06:00:00+01:00" end="2019-12-31T04:00:00+01:00">
    <room name="Lecture room 11"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 14-15"/>
    <room name="Seminar room 13"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M1"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M2"/>
    <room name="Lecture room M3"/>
    <room name="Kidspace"/>
    <room name="CCL Saal 3"/>
    <room name="Chaos West Bühne"/>
    <room name="ChaosZone"/>
    <room name="OIO Stage">
      <event id="356" guid="6eeb1e22-ff82-54be-af15-08e562eca26f">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T12:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>12:00</start>
        <duration>00:30</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>GGV8G3</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/GGV8G3/</url>
        <title>Cryptography of Killing Proof-of-Work [YBTI/wefixthenet session]</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We briefly discuss the range of cryptographic primitives being used by protocols that seek to make proof-of-work protocols obsolete. We shall focus primarily on these cryptographic building blocks themselves, not overly on the different protocols built form them.</abstract>
        <description>There are a handful of protocols consuming enormous amounts of energy in proof-of-work schemes, which provide only rather tenuous security assurances. In practice, proof-of-work also invalidates these protocols original goal of being distributed.&#13;
&#13;
There is also a zoo of protocols designs, both new and from the 80s, that provide far stronger security than proof-of-work at minimal cost. We shall discuss the distinctive cryptographic primitives used by these protocols, without examining any of these critters too closely.&#13;
&#13;
In essence, our taxonomy splits as blind signatures vs. verifiable random functions (VRFs) vs. randomness beacons, with the latter consisting of publicly verifiable secret sharing (PVSS) and verifiable delay functions (VDFs). We only have time for a cursory look at the mathematics usable to build each of these, but this should explain some of their uses, strengths, and weaknesses.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="128">
            <code>MCE83P</code>
            <public_name>dvn</public_name>
            <biography>p2p communications and privacy researcher and developer&#13;
&#13;
Currently organizing a "youbroketheinternet/wefixthenet" session at 36c3, representing GNUnet.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="130">
            <code>BQ99TB</code>
            <public_name>Jeffrey Burdges</public_name>
            <biography>Jeff Burdges is an applied cryptography researcher working with the [Web3 foundation](https://research.web3.foundation/en/latest/), where he works on cryptography for decentralized and/or privacy preserving protocols.&#13;
&#13;
Jeff's work often involves collaborative randomness, specialized signature schemes like verifiable random functions (VRFs) or anonymous credentials, and increasingly both zero-knowledge proofs and incentives or mechanism design using VRFs.  Jeff is also researching a peer-to-peer private messaging service that will use mix networks.&#13;
&#13;
Jeff previously worked on [Taler](https://taler.net/en/) and [GNUNet](https://gnunet.org/en/) as a postdoc for Christian Grothoff at Inria, Rennes, where he worked on anonymity protocols primarily mix networks, blind signatures, security proofs, distributed authentication, forward-secure ratchets, and pairing-based protocols.  Jeff holds a PhD degree in Mathematics from Rutgers University in New Jersey.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="372" guid="809d07c4-a9c7-5004-811e-409aa6bf4296">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T12:40:00+01:00</date>
        <start>12:40</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>B3TZGV</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/B3TZGV/</url>
        <title>Going fully Foss! A non-profits adventure in building a completely FOSS IT environment.</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>In this talk we'll dive into the challenge of going fully FOSS. We'd like to introduce you to the principles behind our decision to choose FOSS. We'll explain the why and how, focusing on ethics as well as our tech stack. We'll share what daily trials and tribulations we had to overcome, how our organization coped with these changes, and what our day to day work now looks like. We'll give an honest review of the cost of choosing FOSS over proprietary software. We'll also detail our migration experience and talk about our efforts to build a global network of other non-profits using FOSS. Finally we'd like to talk about our relationship with the FOSS community. Our goal of sharing our FOSS adventure is to show other organizations that it is important and possible to choose ethical IT alternatives.</abstract>
        <description>Imagine if you could banish all proprietary software out of your workplace and use only free and opensource software. Would it be possible? How would you build this? What technical skills do you need? Will your coworkers appreciate the change? Can you rely on free and opensource apps in a production environment without support? These were all questions we had to answers when we embarked on our FOSS adventure. In 2017 the Mama Cash foundation committed itself to building an entirely new IT environment with as much free and opensource software as possible. Through our activism we recognized the importance of FOSS for non-profits who can't rely on proprietary cloud solutions, for privacy, ethical or financial reasons. As we committed ourselves to the Feminist Principles of the Internet, we quickly realized that using FOSS was the preferred option. The FOSS community has been immensely successful in advocating the use of opensource alternatives. However, implementing these in a business settings is a whole different story. While many organizations would like to contribute to a GAFAM-less world, a combination of lack of experience, knowledge and support prevents them from doing so. Our objective is to show the world that it is possible to build an ethical IT environment that respects open standards, community building and data privacy. &#13;
&#13;
In this talk we'll dive into the challenge of going fully FOSS. We'd like to introduce you to the principles behind our decision to choose FOSS. We'll explain the why and how, focusing on ethics as well as our tech stack. We'll share what daily trials and tribulations we had to overcome, how our organization coped with these changes, and what our day to day work now looks like. We'll give an honest review of the cost of choosing FOSS over proprietary software. We'll also detail our migration experience and talk about our efforts to build a global network of other non-profits using FOSS. Finally we'd like to talk about our relationship with the FOSS community. Our goal of sharing our FOSS adventure is to show other organizations that it is important and possible to choose ethical IT alternatives.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="137">
            <code>PCJYPA</code>
            <public_name>segal</public_name>
            <biography>Ich reiche Vorträge für about:freedom hier ein.</biography>
          </person>
          <person id="146">
            <code>8VCF8M</code>
            <public_name>Gina Plat</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="364" guid="5eed96a6-5814-5798-a584-9581c8dd23ea">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T13:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>13:50</start>
        <duration>00:55</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>BBL8YL</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/BBL8YL/</url>
        <title>SNAC - The only way to beat Facebook</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 45 minutes + 10 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>The current social media situation is catastrophic. A single megacorporation controls the entire digital life of large parts of the world's population. Together with the rapidly improving methods for processing this data, a power that not only concerns experts is being bundled here. And Facebook's monopoly secures itself. On the one hand, users cannot leave Facebook(/ Instagram/WhatsApp) without being cut off from the social life of their friends. On the other hand, alternatives fail because they can't reach a critical mass. It seems impossible that a single application will ever replace Facebook. The freedom of the Internet is fundamentally threatened. Breaking the power of Facebook is probably one of the greatest challenges of our time. And in order to solve this task, we did come up with a detailed concept that we want to present to the public for the first time at 36c3.&#13;
SNAC - Social Network Application Cluster - is the name of the protocol used to standardise data exchange between different social media applications. Just as email protocols enable users to choose their provider freely, this protocol should also enable greater diversity in this area. It is easy to see that a single application isn't able to satisfy the needs of every single user. With SNAC we enable a decentralized structure, where each user can choose his server, but also his client application, from a broad spectrum. By developing our pilot application Open Source, we make it easy for other developers to integrate their own applications into the network.&#13;
But the decentralized Open Source dream alone is not enough to revolutionize the social media world. In order for the new applications emerging in SNAC to be able to run, an appropriate economic environment is needed to cover the operating costs. If the user accesses many different servers while surfing through the decentralized network, the question arises who is responsible for the access costs caused. There is a lack of a corresponding micropayment service with which it is possible to pay very small amounts easy and securely. At first glance, this seems like a project of its own, but it is closely linked to the operation of a decentralised social network. And there are several  advantages emerging by linking social networks with a micropayment system. For example, users can donate a few cents to the creators of content they value, which then adds up to a fair reward for the creators. And this is done directly, independently and without forced ads for the users. But the mental alarm bell of data security rightly rings here when one tries to link financial and private communication data. Therefore, it is all the more important to hand over data sovereignty to the user when planning the protocols and to leave the server operators only the task for which they are fairly paid - the operation of the servers.&#13;
We are currently putting this concept into protocols that enable secure transactions and protect the user's data. The aim is to create an environment where everyone has the chance to honestly and transparently pay the costs they incur instead of filling the pockets of corporations with their data. &#13;
Our project is quite daring, that is clear to us. And yet we are sure that this is exactly what we want to do in the coming years. Because there is a chance that we will find 15 crazy people who want to develop this utopia together with us. There's a chance we'll find 50,000 people supporting us with an average of 1€ a month to feed our 15 crazy developers. There's a chance that we can create an environment where many small subnets with cool innovative applications can trigger a movement that's going to be so big it will overcome Facebook's monopoly. And above all, we can create an environment where technology benefits people again, rather than the other way around. &#13;
If 36c3 isn't the right place for a project like this, what else is? We will give a talk in which we will discuss a better world and the difficulties that lie on the path there. We want to encourage listeners to think and participate, but above all we are also there to initiate a discussion. We want to hear all the concerns and mistakes that we overlook and we need the expertise from all the different angles that only the CCC brings together. We will subject our protocols and a first instance of a microbank to the endurance test, the hackers of Leipzig.</abstract>
        <description>Hi! We're offeringa bit of a different talk, where we want to present a project that might bring a renaissance to the independence and freedom of the internet. We want to dream together of a better world, but then also talk about the concrete steps that need to be done to get there.</description>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="134">
            <code>AYAEA9</code>
            <public_name>Steffen</public_name>
            <biography>Computer Scientist from Tübingen, adventurer travelling the world with his VW-Bus, part of the family since 33c3. Passionate about restoring the integrity of the internet in the social media sector.</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="345" guid="797c2897-5903-57ae-9ad2-f5d4a9b5a79c">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T14:50:00+01:00</date>
        <start>14:50</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>BFEFPM</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/BFEFPM/</url>
        <title>Internet access and VoIP as Open/Commons Infrastructure</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>Some Initiatives are trying to provide internet access and VoIP dial-out in a user-owned (Commons Economy) or completely open infrastructure. We will present the state of affairs and invite to a discussion on the possible perspectives.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="121">
            <code>MWCBCT</code>
            <public_name>Sumy</public_name>
            <biography>Active in Freifunk, TeleCommons, community networks</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
      <event id="380" guid="9f137ade-314d-5531-9e55-e0020824464a">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T17:30:00+01:00</date>
        <start>17:30</start>
        <duration>00:25</duration>
        <room>OIO Stage</room>
        <slug>GM9RV3</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/GM9RV3/</url>
        <title>Closing Session</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Talk 20 minutes + 5 minutes Q&amp;A</type>
        <language>de</language>
        <abstract>Verabschiedung und Details zum Abbau</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="7">
            <code>USJAK9</code>
            <public_name>Andreas Bräu</public_name>
            <biography/>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
    <room name="Workshop">
      <event id="346" guid="51138520-7dc9-5c59-997b-76c4d0ca9f24">
        <logo/>
        <date>2019-12-30T15:00:00+01:00</date>
        <start>15:00</start>
        <duration>02:00</duration>
        <room>Workshop</room>
        <slug>XJHFPM</slug>
        <url>https://talks.oio.social/36c3-oio/talk/XJHFPM/</url>
        <title>Internet access and VoIP as Open/Commons Infrastructure</title>
        <subtitle/>
        <track/>
        <type>Workshop 2 hours</type>
        <language>en</language>
        <abstract>We want to explore the perspectives and plan future action on internet access and VoIP dial-out in a user-owned (Commons Economy) or completely open infrastructure. See the related talk for an introduction to the state of affairs.</abstract>
        <description/>
        <recording>
          <license/>
          <optout>false</optout>
        </recording>
        <persons>
          <person id="121">
            <code>MWCBCT</code>
            <public_name>Sumy</public_name>
            <biography>Active in Freifunk, TeleCommons, community networks</biography>
          </person>
        </persons>
        <links/>
        <attachments/>
        <answers/>
      </event>
    </room>
  </day>
</schedule>
